RG 140, Connecticut State Dental Association
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Dental Association records
1864-1965
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Dental Association
4.5 cubic feet
The Connecticut State Dental Association is a statewide, professional membership organization representing Connecticut licensed dentists. It was established in 1864, and incorporated in 1876.
RG140
1932-072
Historical Note
The Connecticut State Dental Association is a statewide, professional membership organization representing Connecticut licensed dentists. It was established in 1864, and incorporated in 1876. According to their website, "The mission of the Connecticut State Dental Association is to educate, advocate, communicate and collaborate on behalf of its members and the public which it serves."
Scope and Content
The records consist of minutes of meetings, reports of conventions and special meetings, scrapbooks, proceedings, applications, miscellaneous printed reports, and a manuscript history of the organization written in 1940 by Dr. R. Bullock Jones. Also included are minutes of meetings of the Board of Censors, 1901-1928, an organization concerned with ethical practices.
Related Material
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut State Dental Association
Persons:
Jones, R. Bullock
Subjects:
Connecticut State Dental Association -- Records and correspondence; Dentistry -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc; Dentists -- Connecticut; Connecticut State Dental Association -- History
Document Types:
Applications; By-laws; Constitutions; Minutes; Correspondence; Proceedings; Reports; Scrapbooks
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
On November 17, 1932 four volumes of the Connecticut Dental Association were deposited at the Connecticut State Library by Dr. C.E. Peterson of Rockville, Connecticut, who was Secretary-Treasurer of the Association. These four volumes included one volume of minutes of the meetings of the Board of Censors, 1921-1927 and three volumes of Proceedings of the 63rd, 64th, 65th, and 66th annual meetings.
In 1975, the Association's records and other material from the State Library's catalog collection were transferred to the State Archives.
Container List
- Records, 1864-1965
  - 1. Records, 1864-1916; 5 volumes (Box 1-2)
    Combination of minutes of meetings, scrapbooks, and reports of conventions and special meetings. Also includes the Constitution and By-Laws of the Association.
    Arranged chronologically.
  - 2. Minutes of the meetings of the Board of Censors, 1901-1928; 2 volumes (Box 2)
    The Board of Censors was concerned with ethical professional practices.
    Dates are not inclusive.
  - 3. Proceedings, 1927-1965
    - 63rd and 64th Annual Meetings, 1927-1928; 1 volume (Volume Item 3)
    - 65th Annual Meetings, 1929; 1 volume (Volume Item 4)
    - 66th Annual Meetings, 1930; 1 volume (Volume Item 5)
    - 1932-1944, 14 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1946-1957, 12 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1958-1965, 9 volumes (Box 8)
  - 4. Report of the Public Health Conference of the Council on Dental Health of the Connecticut State Dental Association, 1953 January 14; 2 copies (Box 8)
    Conference was held at Hotel Taft in New Haven, Connecticut.
  - 5. Membership applications, 1900-1914 (Box 9)
    Unarranged.
  - 6. Miscellaneous printed reports, 1876-1939 (Box 9)
  - 7. History of Dentistry in Connecticut, 1964-1939 by Dr. R. Bullock Jones, 1940; manuscript copy,; 6 volumes
    - Chapters 1-21, 3 volumes (Box 10)
    - Chapter 22, 2 volumes (Box 11)
    - Chapters 14, 17, 1 volume (Box 11)
      Contains some additional information on "Dental Patriotism, 1916-1918" from chapter 14 and "Dr. Charles McManus, 1865-1940" from chapter 17 which were in earlier volumes.